Okay, we are starting and recording. I
am admitting everyone.
Hello and good afternoon everybody or
good evening I should say. We are uh
starting the meeting but uh we have a
few people who are still logging in. So
as they are being admitted, I'll go
through some of the normal um items that
we do uh as far as for our um uh going
through our usual um uh beginning
stages. So for those who do not know me,
I am Dominic Zerllo and I am the center
director at the New Mexico Department of
Health with the Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin. And I'm joined
here by a couple of our colleagues. So
I'll have them introduce themselves at
this point. Jorge, if you would go ahead
and introduce yourself.
>> Good evening everyone. Thank you for
being here and thank you for your
contributions. My name is Jorge
Gonzalez. I'm the medical psilocybin
program manager.
>> Okay.
>> Uh Adrian.
>> Good afternoon. My name is Adrian
Estrada. I am a health educator with the
medical cannabis and psilocybin program.
>> Thank you. Adrian Ishmael,
>> I apologize there. I'm just fixing my
table. Uh, good afternoon. It seems
really bright there. Good evening. Um,
my name is Isma Zutad. I'm also one of
the health educators here uh at the
Center for Medical Cannabis and
Silicide. And thank you everyone for
attending.
>> Great. Thank you, Ishmael. And uh, Dr.
Robert Truckner, if you could just go
ahead and introduce yourself.
Hi everybody. I'm Robert Shreker. I'm
the medical director for the medical
psilocybin and cannabis programs. I'm
thrilled to be here and I'm interested
to hear what y'all say.
Okay. And so that is our team uh from
the medical cannabis and psilocybin
program and center. Um, and so just as a
reminder for everybody is we do record
these meetings. And so since we are
recording them, we do ask that everybody
uh be a little cautious with their
language. In other words, no profanity.
Um, we do have to bleep it out otherwise
because they are these recordings are
put on our website. And along with that,
that is part of the reason why um
outside of the team and the board
members, we do not actually have cameras
on. And the reason for that is just in
case there is something in the
background. But the secondary reason for
that is so that we can ensure that as
people are actually um uh that people
are able to connect on the internet
because we do know that some areas of
the state internet can be a little
spotty at times and so we want to make
sure that we are able to have people on
as much as possible and the video just
unfortunately causes people to drop off
on a regular basis and so we would much
rather have people here even though you
may not be able to see faces rather than
have people not be here and so uh I hope
that you all understand that. Um and at
this point um I believe uh Desba uh is
well I don't believe Desba is the chair
of this committee and uh so Desba if you
would like to introduce yourself and
then uh I'll turn it on over to you.
Oh, Desba, if you're speaking, your mic
is still muted.
>> And it looks like Despa just dropped and
is rejoining. Speaking of internet
connectivity, sorry, everyone. Yeah. Um
well, while that's happening, what I
will just go ahead and do while Desba
rejoins is um uh just uh some of the
again some of the other housekeeping
sort of items and I'll be putting some
of this in the chat as well. Um but just
as a reminder, if you have questions
with regard to the program or would like
to go to the websites and see them, then
they are on these links that I have on
the screen at the moment and that I am
putting in the chat. If you have
questions or you would like to submit
written comment after the meeting and
would like to do that then uh what you
would want to do is send it to our email
at medical.silocybin
dooh.nm.gov
and I am putting those requirements in
the chat as well. Uh, and uh,
let's see. Um,
and Desba, have you been able to rejoin?
>> Dominic, look at uh, for some reason it
keeps it just says admitting. I don't
know if you see that.
>> I I do see that.
>> Okay.
>> So, I'm not sure. It looks like Desba
may be having some connectivity issues,
everyone. So, um, with that in mind,
what we can go ahead and do at this
point, um, hopefully Desba will be able
to join us here shortly. Um,
um, but in the meantime, if there are
individuals who would like to introduce
themselves,
um, if you don't mind putting your hand
up and then we'll go ahead and call on
you and, uh, be able to have you
introduce yourselves. Well, one more
time. So, it looks like Desba may have
been able to join. Despa, are you here?
>> Yes, finally.
>> Perfect. Thank you. So, Desba, if we
just went through some of the logistics.
So, if you want to introduce yourself
and then we just asked if there was
anyone else who wanted to introduce
themselves to raise their hands. So, uh
while Desba, while you introduce
yourself, anyone else who would like to
do so, please raise your hand and we
will, uh, call on you shortly.
>> Yes. So, um I'm Desba and I'm um
chairing the equity, access, and
cultural considerations meeting. Um we
have had a couple of meetings so far. Um
and um I'm here in Santa Fe, New Mexico
for some of you who don't know where I'm
at. And yeah, I would definitely love to
have uh more people um who are new to
um introduce yourselves if you would
like to. Um we have gone over a couple
of different um
uh topics in the past and concerns from
the community and we have uh come up
with a list of some of those things. Um
right now the legislature legislation is
still in session so we're going to be
hearing more back from that and then
being able to move forward from there.
Um so there's just a little bit of a lag
time also too for some people who are
new um tribal uh governance has been in
uh concern to get more of the tribes
involved in New Mexico since we have um
23 different distinct tribes here. Um
and we're also um sort of waiting on
being able again with legislation to be
able to go um through with allowing the
governors to settle in and um they
change every year for those who are not
aware. Um yeah, so I definitely would
like for people to introduce themselves.
Let's see. We have
Yeah, that'd be great. And then if you
have any other quick question, sorry I
was late. I keep thinking that there is
like an not an issue with either the
camera or the links or something and I
had to have someone reboot my computer
and I completely destroyed all my
passwords and everything. So that and
all my settings for my camera. So then I
didn't realize that that had been
happening. So yeah, if anybody would be
interested in in uh telling me who's
here um that would be great.
>> Yeah, we have uh Kate Hawk there with
her hand up. Uh Kate, please uh
introduce yourself when ready.
>> Everybody, I'm Kate Pac. I'm in Santa Fe
and I've been working with psychedelics
and trauma for over 40 years. I've been
a MAPS member that whole time. I've ran
the Native American Trauma Project and I
lived in Arizona in on and around the
Navajo Nation for all that time, but I'm
in Santa Fe now. Um, we host the Santa
Fe Psychedelic Society here and um, I've
done the Colorado Natural Medicine
facilitator licensing and the MAPS MDMA
licensing. So, I'm really interested in
having more accent and especially um,
the native communities here. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have uh, Chz Fleming. Uh, pardon me if I
got that wrong. I've enabled your mic.
Please begin when ready and uh let me
know how one pronounces that.
So just to let you know uh I've enabled
your mic but you have to unmute
yourself. Uh if you're finding any
difficulty in that process uh there have
been instructions posted by um our
director Dominic Zuro in the chat. Um,
if you're still finding difficulties,
>> yes, we do. Fantastic.
>> Thanks. My name's Chis Fleming. I live
in Qua. I'm Chico. I've been in New
Mexico my whole life. I'm a psychedelic
micologist with over 30 years
experience. I published a cultivation
manual on um, salosy, the bulk
cultivation of salosi. I teach magic
mushroom classes through the native root
school based out of TA and I have a rare
condition called cluster headache that I
treat with psilocybin.
>> Thank you very much for sharing that.
Next we have Gregory Evans. Gregory I
have enabled your mic. Please unmute
yourself when ready and go ahead.
Um, hi, my name is Gregory Evans. I am
an independent researcher and home
micologist with no affiliations. I am a
Santa Fe resident. My intention here is
to support the program's development
through committee recommendations
aligned with emerging research and best
practices. Um, as well as that, I'm very
glad to see that you made it here,
Chevy. And um, yeah, Kate, it's always
good to see you. Good talk last night.
Thank you very much for that.
>> And Desba, thank you so much for hosting
this.
>> Thank you very much for sharing. Next,
we have Brett Phelps. Brett, I have
enabled your microphone. Please unmute
when ready and begin.
>> Hi, good evening everybody. Uh, this is
Brett Phelps here. Um, I am an attorney
based out of Las Vegas, New Mexico and
living in in Mora, New Mexico. Um,
particularly interested in this
committee to see what we can do to um
provide rural access for all of us
people living out in the the far reaches
of our state. So, thanks to Desba and
Dominic and the rest of the team,
everybody working on this.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have Katherine Waro.
Katherine, I have enabled your
microphone. Please unmute yourself and
begin when ready.
>> Hello everyone. Thank you so much. Uh
especially I want to take a moment to
thank um the board.
>> Believe we're experiencing some
technical issues there. Does anyone Can
you Can you hear Katherine? Um
>> no, I can't hear.
>> Okay. um you've uh dropped off there. Uh
if you'd like to start again, um give it
another go. Uh if you're experiencing
technical difficulties sometimes, uh
>> that there we go. Hello.
>> Yeah, I don't know what happened there,
so I don't know how far I got, but I'll
just say my name is Katherine Waro. I'm
located in Los Cusus. I am a licensed
counselor. Um I'm a huge advocate for
the healing properties um of this
amazing medicine. And I'd like I'm here
mostly because I want to contribute in
any way possible. Um I do have some
experience using this medicine. I'm also
um I have a colleague who is currently
in Mexico and has connected with Maria
Sabina's
um daughter and they have asked to be a
part of all of this and I didn't know if
that's something that we would be
interested or not but I thought I would
pose it to the group. um she would
require a translator if that's something
that everyone's interested in. I know we
want um a lot of voices from New Mexico.
So, I wasn't sure if um offering this to
the group would be something of interest
or not, but I very much um want to make
sure that that is an option if anyone's
interested. Thank you very much for
being here everybody.
>> Thank you very much. Next we have
Meredith.
Meredith, I I have enabled your
microphone. Please begin when ready.
>> Hi. Um, I am a future practitioner. I
guess I'm applying to programs in
clinical psychology this fall. Um, and
I'm specifically interested in working
with justice impacted folks and hoping
to incorporate psychedelic assisted
therapies into my future practice. So,
um, really important to have equity and
access. Um, and I'm excited to be here
and learning. So, thank you all.
>> Thank you very much for that. Finally,
we have Zoe Sperolitoss. Uh, pardon me
if I have pronounced that incorrectly. I
have enabled your microphone. Um, you
may begin when ready.
again to unmute. Uh the instructions
have been placed in the chat by uh our
director Dominic Zerlo. If there are any
um technical difficulties that you may
be experiencing, often it may be the
case that dropping off the call and
joining back in may um
may solve those issues. Uh so may
perhaps attempt those uh if no other
solution is found. Um whenever you do
get the opportunity to speak uh just uh
raise your hand again and we can try and
get that going.
>> So just received a message in the chat.
Uh Zoe says it's happening again. Uh
she's in reference to the previous uh
committee meeting. Uh she had microphone
issues I believe. Uh but she will type
in the chat. So that will be we shall
await something there. In the meantime,
Desba, I shall pass it back over to
yourself.
>> Okay. All right. Um but yeah, so it's
I'm a little limited because I had to
log in on my phone um to be able to see
everybody here, but um so yeah. So thank
you all for introducing yourselves. And
if there's anybody else, I see more
people. Um so far it has been mostly
just kind of a listening session with um
just trying to get um understanding of
different people. I would just implore
you all to continue to share the links
and um what's important to you in the
rural areas um because
what part of this equity access is is
just to understand the different um
areas of New Mexico that there is access
and what that looks like. What does that
look like to everyone? So far it seems
it's been um financial uh needs. We're
also looking into um I think the patient
fund which is also another legislative
item um that needs to be addressed and
we need to kind of wait for until that
is all set and um done. We're going to
be done with the legislation I think
February 20th I believe. Um and so
there's just kind of a little bit of a
lag and a waiting period for some of
these um issues that need to really be
um resolved. But in the meantime, it's
just kind of looking at like what are
the different um areas of the state
really need um at less
to be done. Um I'm looking to really the
communities. What has been discussed in
the last meeting was um
was the possibility of going out into
the communities and doing one-on-one
in-person
listening sessions um in the future. Um
and again after this legislation is done
that might be something we are looking
into. I definitely want to be able to
look into it and then also um when we
get together with the board also um
having conversations with all the other
committees if that's something that's
possible maybe not all of us can go um
but this is something that I'm
presenting to the people that are
attending here and to talk amongst um
your other networks you know I'm hearing
Los Cusus I'm hearing TA um I'm hearing
MA people who are there um also Espanola
area. This is where I'm from. You know,
I also have ties to family in
Farmington. Um, you know, what does it
look like in all these different areas?
The needs of people in Roswell are going
to be slightly different than those that
are in say Raton. And this doesn't just
go with um patients. This also goes with
facilitators, administr um administers,
administerers
um and anyone else who is going to be um
facilitating this medicine to patients.
Um it also goes to how we are going to
proceed with I guess divvying up or pro
seeing like who is actually going to be
able to um what is equity look like when
it comes to the patients um in in these
different areas. Is it going to be just
regional? Is it going to be um
socioeconomic demographic? Um and then
also again the cultural considerations.
I don't want to just say the cultural
considerations are only specific to
Native Americans, but I also don't want
to dismiss the fact that there are um
Native American um concerns. I will
point this out. I'm I'm not sure how
many Native American people that I'm
seeing in this particular call. I'm not
saying that we all have to be in here in
this in this particular committee. um
just because I am like the Native
American um B board member that is a
part of this. What my main concern is
mostly that how does that look like as
far as like an indigenous um
reciprocity? What does it look like when
it comes to reaching out into the
communities? What is what is since since
especially coming from the Native
American point of view, the government
hasn't always kept up to its promises
when it comes to Native Americans and
abiding by the treaties and providing
the access. So what does that really
look like if we are able to provide that
not only to Native American communities
but also the real rural communities and
anywhere else in between? I know I've
heard also that um cost is also um a
huge concern whether it means uh
cultivators people who are in the
propagation
um them being able to have do the tests
what does that look like so this is also
different intersections of where equity
access and cultural considerations is
really important to understand
what that means in terms of propagation
what that means in terms of research
what that means in terms of um
uh pre present like what's being
presented, you know, understanding um
that it's not a one-sizefitsall kind of
deal. Um and then I feel that in some
ways that might be what other states may
have lacked or in other terms in other
ways um that's not associated with
psilocybin um where we have failed or
where the government essentially has
failed. So this is an opportunity to
make those rights um to actually turn
things around in New Mexico. This is why
I really feel like it's important to get
out into the actual communities and have
these kinds of conversations to really
see what's going on. But then that means
traveling to say the Navajo Nation or to
the border towns which is Gallup which
is going to Farmington um or what it
even means to go into different
communities where their belief systems
are completely vastly different than say
what might be here in Santa Fe for
instance. Um, and I think it's really
important to find out what those
barriers are that may be either
psychological, financial, um, or when it
comes to transportation. That's why
we're looking into tellaalth and what
those programs. But I'm really wanting
to find out the information from people
what's really of a concern. Part of the
issue is though, like I said, is that
there are intersections with the other
committees that are really important to
also take into consideration. I can be
on my soap box all day long and tell you
what I feel like is really important to
like for us to like look into, but this
is where it comes into having people
join the committees and saying this is
what we want to see and making sure that
um not only do we say what is important
but then also just realizing that there
are a little bit of limitations into how
this is being rolled out and what are
the restrictions
um or considerations, not restrictions,
but considerations that need to be um
understood by the end of the year. Um
I'm not sure if anyone else's feeling
has a concern in line with what I've
just said. Um
but I know like I said, we've heard
issues of tellahalth. What is the
tellaalth going to look like when it
comes to um understanding who needs the
medicine? What are the um based on the
presenting conditions? The um committee
has the ability to add on to as far as I
know what those presenting conditions
are that are approved by the department
which is we can make the recommendations
to the department. So I'm like a bridge.
I'm the bridge and this committee is the
bridge and the advisory board is the
bridge to
allow more people to provide more input.
But that means we need more input. I'll
put this in a different context. If we
only have limited input into AI when
we're using chat GPT, we're going to get
limited output.
So this is where we need the public to
really kind of come in. If we're saying
that cactuses are only supposed to be
green and we're not take into
consideration that somewhere they're
sometimes white or yellow,
we're only going to be seeing green
cactuses in the output section. Okay.
So, I really need your help when it
comes into saying what what programs we
need, how are we going to do the
education, um what your communities um
need as far as uh
being talked to or listened to really
essentially is what it is. Um, so I'm
hoping um that we can kind of figure out
how we're going to be going into the
communities and providing these like
what what the differences and it might
be in in um Espanola versus um Los
Cruises. And I feel like I'm just a
broken record at this point. Um
hopefully Zoe maybe did you able to like
put something in the chat that you
wanted to share? Okay, we did.
Okay, let's see. Um, I'll go ahead and
read what Ro Zoe said if if uh Jorge and
uh Dominic don't mind. Uh my name is Zoe
and I'm going to mess this up. Spry
Ratoss and I am a psych uh nurse
practitioner and professor in Buffalo,
New York. Bird and snow. Oh no. Gez, I
know what that's like. I used to live on
the east coast for a while. I was
invited by a colleague who teaches in
New Mexico and I was interested because
this is my area of research and I'd like
to bring into practice. I am very
familiar with the topic of equity,
access and cultural considerations.
I can give more detail on that a
different time but wanted to at least
say hello and thank you for having me.
Okay. Um I have been trying to write
down and keep track of like who's been
in the meetings just on my own. Um, and
I'm not sure if we have heard from Zoe
before. I know that there was someone
who was also in No, I don't think we
have. I think that person was also a
lawyer. Um, but yes, glad to have you
here, Zoe. And definitely want to be
able to have more input on um
researchbased um equity access and
considerations.
Oh, this is your first time. Okay,
great. First time first time caller.
Yay. Hi. Thank you for being here. Um,
it's unfortunate. Keep trying with your
microphone. I don't know if we can try
again because it would be great to just
have you um pro provide more input um
based on what you have to offer. Um
okay,
historical reckoningness I'm doing. Yes.
Yeah. So, I mean another part of that is
so and this is on my phone. Just bear
with me. I'm so sorry that I I'm
actually really not this technically
inept, although it is apparent that I am
at this point right now. Um, I generally
am not. My dad and my parents always
asking me for help and it just I'm going
to blame Microsoft. I will say that on
record. I'm
I'm just not familiar with it as much as
I would like to be. Um, but yeah, it's
it's it kind of just goes back to,
you know, there's there's there's the
governance part, right? I'm going to try
to see if I can break this up into
several different sections as well.
There's the governance part. There is
there is government and I want to just
point that out. Yes, I we are part of
I'm a liaison with this. This is kind of
basically where I feel like I'm always
in between. They have it. I'm going to
use this phrase in a different way.
It's like I'm neither here nor there.
And I kind of feel that in a sense like
not only culturally because my mom is um
you know she was from Mexico um and then
my father is Native American and then I
grew up in northern New Mexico which is
predominantly Hispanic
um Spanishspeaking culture there and I
did not grow up on the reservation. So
there's a lot of code switching that I
feel like is important that we also
understand where there's the government
and like I said historical facts what
has done in the past and that there was
this there is this natural medicine as
um Katherine had pointed out Maria
Sabina we all are aware of of the
historical context of psychedelic
mushrooms
um but there has been this medicine
there is this medicine and you know But
what does it look like to make sure and
maintain now in this context of the
state of New Mexico as as a part of the
United States of America? What does it
look like when we have a responsibility
to establish care and provide you know
like working with and also against
itself where this quote uh human right I
feel was taken away in some ways. And
why why was it taken away? um because
brown people had medicine
and that was not a good thing.
Government take it away and now we have
to work backwards. I feel in this
context of like what do we do now?
Whereas it might be great to sit there
and just say let's take this away. We
are under these constraints and these
limitations and these restrictions that
are in place and until they are lifted,
we have this work to do to have a
responsibility to allow within these
constraints um public and the people who
really need to have access to this
medicine. It may seem for all intents
and purposes that it seems backwards and
I totally get you and I understand that.
Um I'm just kind of giving my soap box.
This is only coming from me in my my
personal capacity.
But that's where like in the capacity as
a part of the board where do those two
things intersect intersect and how do we
meet the need as well as also trying to
move ahead as a society to a place that
is more whole. Right? And that's where
I'm trying to get back to the soap box
thing. um when it comes to indigenous
um wisdom and spirituality that is we
cannot um dismiss from the medicine
is um you know there's this idea of
trying to regulate this medicine and I
get it's kind of really just all out
there but how do we give back and I feel
like that's part of where this equity
access and cultural considerations
really kind of starts
being um a place where we go into the
communities and understand um what is
needed there and if and and and allowing
them the agency to have the choice of
doing so that it's there if they need it
and what are we going to do and
implement and what are those
recommendations that the community has.
It's not up to us to go do it, but the
department will be the ones to figure
out how to do it. And we can only say
this is the best way that we feel is
possible to do so, and these are our
recommendations to the department um to
provide that. Um and again, that's why
it's saying, you know, it's going out
into the community. For the longest
time, you know that
we have people saying that this is how
you're supposed to give birth or this is
how you're supposed to be done. And we
all know may or may not be true. The
recommendations are you do such and such
a things to be able to take care of um
people. But this is where we we have an
opportunity to
um
do better. And that's why I'm saying it
like it falls on on on the rest of us.
Um so we it's a it's about possible like
apprenticeship having the reciprocity
being responsible with um our um
as a committee as a board to make these
recommendations but it's also part of
the comm community's responsibility to
say to speak up right that's that's kind
of also where I'm getting speaking up
and like saying um we're we we have a
fear or we have a concern or this is the
thing that we feel like has happened
before in the past or you know this is
we're ready for it when are you going to
roll it out or you know we have so and
so number of people but we have this
need that needs to be met in order for
it to happen
um but we also need to these are some
questions that I had thought of um or I
didn't think of them but these questions
that came to me um is
what is our relationship to the
community and how can the board be able
to provide that equity access and those
and those considerations. Um like I
said, there's going to be a different
region in the northwest area than there
is going to be in the southeast area of
New Mexico is different than the cities
are going to look. Um and what needs to
happen there. Um and then also too like
there
we can't just kind of go and say that
this is beneficial medicine and tell
people you need to have this right. It
needs to be coming from a place that
there's a conversation and there's a
dialogue with the community and what
they really need and saying hey um and
that's where the education comes. I feel
like this is a lot of is education. All
right. I'm gonna see if there's anybody
that's wanting to talk at this point
because um like I said, I'm on my phone.
No. Okay. Um
yeah. So, in the meantime, I do have
different um been working with trying to
get a set of definitions. So, I've asked
for the help of the department um to
kind of get through what needs to be um
taken care of, but also just realizing
that there are um recommendations that
we can provide. But we do have a duty as
the um chair to provide
what like what does um
let's see
try like I said trying to meet the
restrictions and trying to meet the
concerns and trying to meet the scope of
what the board is establishing as
recommendations to the department And um
so there's like there's responsibilities
that we have on this part of providing
these um recommendations and also
understanding that New Mexico is
different than Colorado, New Mexico is
different than Oregon, but also
understanding that maybe some of the
information that we have say from New
York or Oregon or Colorado or any of
other places that they're doing either
research or clinical trials may have
kind of um come across as far as like
what's important um and other research
areas that um may or may not have
happened. So, I do need that input from
people. I don't know if Zoe is has tried
again to see if she can get her
microphone to work. And I don't know,
Dominic, if you had something that you
wanted to say or not.
Yeah, I I would just say something that
would be really helpful would actually
be to talk about what sort of um
requirements there would be with regard
to the equity fund um and ensuring that
we get it out to people other than
income. And the reason I say that is
because income is the easy one. you
know, we could set up a system, for
example, of who would be eligible for
the equity fund based on, you know, for
example, are they at 200 or 300% of
poverty level or a percentage of that.
But the areas that we really need to
know and that that really I think are
going to be important to ensure that
there is that acqu access and equity
with regard to that fund and being able
to help pay for whether it be treatments
or transportation
um you know interpreters as Katherine
kind of brought up uh earlier um you
know how exactly we do that through the
equity fund. What are those other areas?
What areas do we need to focus on? And
it's easy to kind of say, oh well, rural
and frontier areas, but what exactly
does that really mean in this context?
Like what are the parameters for that?
And how do we do that? And so what would
be helpful for us is to have
recommendations on and not necessarily
right now like the exact aspect of like,
you know, saying, well, we consider
rural to be so many people within so
many square miles. We don't need that
part, but what areas do we need to focus
on? What are some of those populations
that are going to have the need for it?
Whether it be, you know, how do we
define that, you know, uh that
marginalization or, you know, that lack
of services. How do we do that? That's
what we really would be helpful for us.
>> Yeah. And I I feel I'm thankful that
you're um bringing that up because
um I feel like
Yeah. I I honestly and I will say this I
don't know right for me in my
perspective I don't know because I'm
here in Santa Fe I'm in some ways siloed
from what the needs are even in Espanola
where you know like where I'm from I
don't I'm not on the ground there to
have that input from the people that are
working with the with the populations
that need it. All I know is that I'm I'm
happy that they have a blue bus, the
RTD, the Rioba, you know, that's going
there, but how reliable is that? And you
know, what does that look like? That
that thing does not run all the time and
it doesn't run. How far does it run? Is
it is you know, how slow is that system?
And that's is that only for you know the
Rio Grande, the Rioba? What does that
look like? And even I mean I used to
live in Boston. and I used to live in
New York and our public transit system
even though we complained about it
breaking down all the time was still
more reliable than what we have here in
New Mexico and that is a very important
aspect to consider.
Again, what's happening in Farmington is
going to be very different than what's
happening in Roswell. Um, and I do need
the input from people in those specific
places in order to understand like what
that looks like for them specifically.
And as far as you know, there is I I'm
probably going to use this wrong, but
the correlation of between the opioid
overdoses in that have risen in Rio
Reba, Santa Fe County, and I believe TA
over the last like year or the beginning
of last year or the beginning of the two
years ago now that we're in a new year.
Um
those
issues and those instances are important
to understand. Domestic violence is also
important to understand. PTSD, like all
the different conditions that are really
important when it looks like, you know,
you have uh urban natives like myself in
Santa Fe. What does that look like? Am I
going to be able is is it gonna is
something gonna happen between the Santa
Fe Indian Health Services or even having
like a liaison between there and you
know Medicaid or you know what are the
what are the pathways that that's going
to look like um and this is where I
seriously need the input from people in
these specific places and I totally
understand that like right now at least
this is my understanding
that we're all super happy that this is
happening. And so our effort and maybe
our mind, some of us, some of us, not
everybody, that's why some of you are
here, is really going into how do we
grow this? How do we get this happen?
How do I get in on this? How do I make
this happen so that I can benefit from
it, right? But then that this is where
to me, this is where the cultural
considerations and the indigenous wisdom
go into play. But what about the people
at the other end that we're actually
trying to be able to help with this,
right? Is yes, it might be great to get
in and have a lucrative business and,
you know, finally we get to have this
going, but the people at the end of that
chain of events is the whole point of
why we're doing this. Is the whole point
is to bring back wholeness. is the whole
point is to be able to to go back into
our communities and and and help the
people
that that need it most.
Um
as I just wanted to quickly say that
there was someone in the chat who has
dropped a line. Um UW Milwaukee and the
state of WI which I'm not familiar with
because I'm not from the US. I'm
assuming that's Wisconsin.
Anyone will correct me on that? I don't
know. Uh had
grant monies to utilize for SUD/AODA
programs in indigenous communities
instead of those state institutions
administrating uh administrating grant
monies. They turned it over to four
nations in the state to create their own
programs to serve their communities
closest to home in the most culturally
aligned means possible.
Okay, I like that. If we can make sure
to take that as a note as far as the
future discussions. Um, is there
anything any followup with that with
um
what and then that kind of goes into
Yeah, I mean that's that's a great
that's a great point of example um for
you know allowing a community to be able
to provide and I'm not sure what the
responsibility New Mexico is too but
this is a this is grant money since we
had grant monies to utilize Or
can you I don't I'm not familiar with
sud. Can we spell that out if you don't
mind? A oa.
>> It's about That's substance use
disorder.
>> Okay. Sorry, I'm not familiar with
>> No, not a problem.
>> Okay. And then the AODA
alcohol, I'm assuming.
>> That one I actually don't know. I've not
we don't utilize that here very much.
Let me see if I can find out. Um
>> meaning let's see accessibility for
Ontarians and disabilities.
That's a is that accessibility
Ontario. That does not say alcohol and
other drug abuse. Okay.
>> Oh, there we go.
>> Okay,
>> that made sense.
>> All right. uh indigenous community said
of those state institutions
administering grant monies, they turned
it o over to foreign nations in the
state to create their own programs to
serve their communities closest to home.
Okay. No, that that sounds like it would
be a good suggestion to look into what
how that can be utilized for native
communities. Um
that's so that's another another good
one. Um, but also again back to this
idea of so then I said sorry
um the acronym AODA made me think about
ADA
um which was Katherine's thing as far as
translators but I was also thinking
accessibility in terms of other
accessibility for other people who need
that. Um, and that is also another
important thing for me as far as uh
accessibility
access. Um, what that really looks like.
Um, but yeah, I like I said, I just
could be on my soap box, but I really
just need the input from other people to
say, you know, these are the things that
we need um to look at and to talk about.
Um and it's not necessarily it it is
both the responsibility of the
department of health to provide these
things but it can only go
part to me at least this is my
understanding part of the reason that
we're doing it in this particular
fashion is so that we don't actually
have this paternalistic look at what
these communities need right and I kind
of go back into this idea of my
geography my geology uh when I was
working for the Navajo Nation
You know, they would say that the
remediation that needed to happen on
Navajo Nation was X, Y, and Z. That was
based out of Philadelphia, that was
based out of New York, that was based
out of New Jersey. You can't, those are
coastal areas, and that landscape is
completely different than what looks
like a Navajo Nation. And you can't sit
there and say that this recommendation
that you have for these coastal
communities and the east coast is going
to be able to be able to be implemented
based on those metrics in Navajo Nation.
It's not going to happen. You need to be
able to landbased
again back to this and everyone is
talking about ancestral wisdom,
indigenous and cultural wisdom. But that
means that these people actually need to
be here to be present to talk about it
also as well. But then we also have to
have the accessibility which again goes
back to this idea of going out into the
communities. That's so important. But
then also having everybody word of mouth
saying that this is really important
that needs to be otherwise we can only
base it on the people who are
participating and wanting to be you know
have that part be having a seat at the
table.
Um and and then also having the
advocates for those who may not be able
to provide that, right? Someone brought
up incarcerated persons. Um and they
really cannot necessarily speak for
themselves at this point. They need an
advocate to say that this is the thing
that needed to happen. But even that um
it needs to be considered, right?
whether or not this is something that we
have the capacity for and the funding
that we have that will come into place
needs to be allocated
um divvied up and provided and how right
and this is just a point that Dominic
was making um
I'll get to the comment in just a second
um but as far as um
how that's going going to look right um
who's actually going to to to be able to
get that and for and for what right um
another and these are the things that I
feel like this is another completely
different analogy just for the sake of
explaining some things we have like a a
couple of major cities in New Mexico um
Albuquerque is the biggest I think and
then I'm I'm forgive me for mis saying
this, but then they have we have Los
Cusus and then we have Santa Fe and then
we also have I think Farmington, Gallup
maybe. Um but there's some of these
bigger but the three main Los Cruus,
Santa Fe, as far as the film industry,
they're considering Los Cusus like a
rural area. Okay,
but even though it's like a city, but
because it's so far down south, it's
considered rural, but the population
might be bigger. And this is where it
kind of gets a little bit tricky when it
comes to how to divvy things up and what
the rules and regulations are about who
gets what.
So when it comes to Santa Fe and and
Albuquerque, we're like the two bigger
cities when it comes to film making. And
so they say, "Oh, we don't need to help
Santa Fe and Albuquerque. We need to
help Los Cusus."
But you think about it, they're all kind
of sort of in these bigger city
categories and they may not necessarily
be to me Las Cruis doesn't seem like
it's that rule to me it's like a city
but in the case of the definitions for
the film industry they consider it rule
right that analogy is the only reason
why I'm saying like this is really
important to have these conversations
about who gets what and what those
presentations what that looks like to be
um considered for the allocating of the
money who gets
exactly okay. So this is I'm hoping that
I'm glad this is I know this is getting
a little off topic but it's just for the
point of illustration
that we like people may not understand
that that's considered rural in some
aspects and it's not. It's a huge city.
All right, I'm going to go to the
comment. Um if you don't mind I'll go
ahead and read it out. This might sound
naive so I apologize. How can we get the
tribes and nations in New Mexico to come
to the table? Um, the representatives.
So, this is kind of a little I touched
on this um
I touched on this a little bit um in the
beginning of the meeting. I just blurted
it out. We are still kind of waiting on
the legislation to die down because all
of the tribal governors and everyone
else is really concerned about what's
going on in the state of New Mexico. and
until they can kind of go back into
their communities and tribes and then we
can have like a formal sitdown with
them. Um that's not going to be able to
move forward just yet. So we are working
on it. Department is working on it um to
be able to have that kind of more formal
sit down and and and talking to in the
meantime
from the comment desk and so forth. Um
there are there is a huge network of
people
um
and I'm just not sure exactly how to
kind of get more people to either come
to the meetings or to um provide input
through the email which is on the screen
saver that Dominic pointed out earlier
in the meeting to have a written
comment.
I'm just going to say this and hopefully
maybe someone can be like, "No, that's
not the case." I have a feeling that
there's might be still a little bit of
the fear of outing oneself.
there's still the possibility of
um repercussions
and that's in part part of the reason
um I provided myself in this way um
to be able to speak for what's needing
to be happen needs to happen here right
>> as well
>> just a quick one I think there's a
there's a hand up in the chat um
>> oh sure great
>> I think it's
Dominic, I think it's your end. Oh,
there you go.
>> It's just me. I I just was was waiting.
It wasn't uh I just really wanted to
give you an update and give everybody a
little bit of an update is I was
speaking with our tribal liaison um
during the public health day at the
roundhouse this last week. And one of
the things we were talking about was
exactly this issue and how to do that.
and uh they are going to continue to
reach out to uh the various tribal and
um uh PBLO governments. But what they
are doing is they are arranging and I
believe it's going to be in March. They
haven't set a date yet, but they are
arranging um a day where they are
inviting all of the um the Native
American governments in New Mexico to a
day where they're going to discuss
different health topics, access issues.
And we are going to have a block of time
during there specifically for
psilocybin. And what that'll do is it
actually helps with regard to some of
the issues you were just bringing up
despa talking as far as outing someone
and doing that because by doing this and
including it an entire day that's
talking about various health issues
we'll be able to get I think better
participation than just if we were doing
it standalone. Um, now that doesn't mean
that we're not going to continue doing
other outreach and other uh, you know,
invitations, things like that. But just
to let you all know, one of the things
that is currently in planning.
>> Thank you for that update.
Um, yeah, I mean, it's it's, you know,
prior prior to getting a part of the
board and also just, you know, there is
concerns um, with insurance. there isn't
concerns with, you know, how is this
going to work andor with Medicaid? How
is it, you know, with with with
everything that's going on? Um,
you know, I feel like there is
definitely more of a need to have this
available.
Um, to the general public, there's a
concern that, you know, should we even
have a regulation in this? Do we just
kind of throw that all out the window?
where that may be a great solution in
some other alternate universe. The way
that we're working right now is in this
constraint of how are we going to roll
out this particular
um medical psilocybin provided to
certain groups of people and others that
we are trying to establish that we
recommend to the department of health
that are recommended to the department
of health. I'll say that again. other
conditions that are recommended to the
Department of Health
um to be able to then have that
and potentially
for the future use in New Mexico. We are
in a particular place that now we have I
think New Jersey on board and they're
doing their thing. Um which is great.
Um, you know, I applaud all the efforts
of all the different ways in which we're
doing it. We have the government saying
we need to have more studies on this. We
have Arizona working on their own
studies. New York, I think, is still
working on a lot of research and
clinical studies as well. Um,
>> um, I believe we also have a hand up by
Dan Houston. So, um,
>> Dan Houston, yes, please speak.
Um, I just have more, I guess, questions
or, um, things I've noticed. Uh, I'm
Daniel just uh, Oregon Rose City
Laboratories. Um, I've been testing in
the industry now three plus years or
whatever it's been. And um I've seen
indigenous or tribal
um affiliate people talk and come and
and and talk about equity and access and
all of that um from day one and some of
these uh different trade shows and stuff
that I go to in the psychedelic
industry. You know, it's very much um
equity and access. Um, but here in
Oregon, I I I would have to actually do
a little bit more research, but I I'm
just off the top of my head, it doesn't
feel like they've gotten involved with
the system. A lot of it has to do with,
in my opinion, expenses and all of that.
Plus, plus um I feel that uh indigenous
tribal people want their
want to be able to continue to do their
rituals in the way they want to consume
it. Um and I feel like Oregon for sure
um has not written it in a fashion that
would allow that to happen. So, um, it
feels like you got to tailor it towards
how the indigenous want to do their
rituals or ceremonies or allow them some
flexibility and barrier of entry really
is cost um, and stuff like that. So, I
don't know, maybe it was a question or
maybe it was a comment. I don't know.
But anyway, that's kind of my two cents.
No, I appreciate your your comment on
that and I will say that I have heard
you know in essentially something
similar um you know from people here in
in this area and just in general um you
know it does kind of get into like a
little bit of a sticky topic and maybe
it's okay that I go ahead and say this
and anyone can go ahead and counter me
and that's totally fine. Um I I can take
it and definitely this is a place to
learn. That's another thing. This is
about listening. I mean we can all and
I'm not saying this specific to you. I'm
talking about myself, you know, we can
all say stupid comments and then it just
be like, no, we can be we can be um uh
educated and being open to listen. Um
but essentially, I feel like that is
partially,
you know, I'm trying to also wrap my
head around like what does that look
like? And I feel like a little bit kind
of left out from my native people out
there um to say, you know, what needs to
happen. And I don't want to speak for
anybody either. Um
that
>> yes
>> and and so and so um
you know, you're right. It needs to be
something that how do what does that
look like? What is the place in which
the Department of Health andor/ New
Mexico and this is probably more like a
legal thing, right? But maybe this is
where we can say like a recommendation
to the department. We can go ahead and
say to the department um we recommend
that the tribes be able to um allow for
themselves, you know, X, Y, and Z,
right? And this just throwing this out
there, not saying that this is the
thing. Um, but this is kind of where
we're looking at what does the tribe,
each tribe and or generally tribes feel
like they need to be able to and how
much leeway,
you know, because we don't also want to
not necessarily this is the right term,
but enttrapment as far as like not
allowing and then allowing. um anyone
who's interested in looking back into
the federal codes with the Navajo Nation
and or anywhere else when it comes to
peyote, which is not discussed here in
psilocybin, medical psilocybin, but the
use of peyote in traditional ceremonies
um was both illegal at some point, you
know, from the federal government. Then
of course, and we have like u um
indigenous tribes not being able to
practice their religions that was given
back to them. Then it was also given to
the Navajo Nation to decide what they
wanted to do, but I think they still
tended to adopt federal government uh
illegality of it and so forth, right?
That kind of gets into this whole sticky
situation. But what are the
recommendations
from
the committee to the department when it
comes to Native Nations being able to
uh decide for themselves how they will
use this andor this is just my two cents
if there is any kind of training
programs or education or outreach as a
liaison from the department that might
need to be able to assist establishing
that kind of infrastructure or facility
or training program to natives that
might need it. I don't know what that
looks like. And I say this again with
the um analogy of working for the Navajo
Nation as a as a geologist.
when it came to uh reclaiming the land
after coal and pea body um coal a coal
extraction from the Navajo Nation,
the Navajo Nation needed to have the
federal government still needs as far as
I know needs the federal government to
come in from Denver to come in and
decide if that land is being remediated
appropriately to give back to the Navajo
Nation. So they would be the
intermediaries between people company
and saying, "Yes, you are doing X, Y,
and Z, right? The grass looks green.
There's no riffs or rallies or anything.
You're good to go." But this takes
decades and still probably not done yet,
right? So, there's the federal
government coming in from Denver helping
the Navajo Nation to remediate the land
back to itself from the coal company.
Right? What Navajo Nation was trying to
do at one point was saying, "We don't
need the federal government to do that.
We can do that on our own." But they had
to show that they could do this. right?
And show that they had the
infrastructure, the training, the
people, the manpower to be able to do
what was being done.
Um, it's very complicated. It's very
legal. But this is what I'm saying is
like what are the recommendations that
we have. I'm trying to say is I don't
want to say that the the tribes can do
whatever they want, which is essentially
what I feel like could be happening,
right? And to the point that the person
made about the monies and the grants,
yes, they can do whatever they want, but
I also feel like because the tribes are
here in New Mexico, then maybe we might
need to provide some kind of uh
sourdough starter to I always use
analogies. I'm sorry. To be able to say,
hey, these are the things that we have
available to you to be able to provide
your own training and your own da da da
da da in your community if you would
like our help.
I feel like that to me is being
responsible and not just hanging the
tribes out to dry to defend defend for
themselves but to do as they wish and
it's available if they want it and I
feel in some ways similar that that can
be also uh working for other
communities.
Um maybe let's just say Roswell doesn't
want to have anything to do with it
despite our better judgment or anyone
else is saying you know or just any
other city right this city is it needs
it so badly let's just go back to
Espanola this city needs it so badly and
you know there's just there's all these
crises that are going on that's a very
paternalistic point of view to say that
this particular place needs it right
it's a different thing to say hey we
have this thing and it would be really
helpful. We have this training if you
want it. We have this. It's shown, you
know, blah blah blah blah blah. What
does that look like? We have vouchers.
We have an equity fund. We have, you
know, this thing to help out with the
eight northern Indian ples council if
they need it. We've reached out to them.
They're on board. You know, these are
the places that you can go to. offering
the possibility and the pathway
is to me what that access looks like.
I'm not saying that like my idea is
great, but I also it needs to be input
from that particular community.
Um, and so that's why I'm saying like
I'm not afraid of saying something
stupid that may not necessarily be the
right thing, but then that gets us to
the thing that might actually need to be
talked about. And maybe saying the wrong
thing or the stupid thing might then
help that community or whatever it is to
say, well, you're not quite right, but
it touched a nerve and it made me think
about what we really need. I'm having
these conversations with my kid right
now. I say, "What about this?" "No."
"What about this?" "No." "What about
this?" "No." And it's really annoying
for both of us that I'm saying the wrong
things. But at some point, we might
actually get to the right thing that
needs to happen. It's a process of
elimination.
And I feel like that's part of what this
board is doing is being responsible to
the citizens of like what can we do,
what needs to be done um in
consideration, not just for the tribes,
but maybe the framework that we provide
to the tribes might actually be able to
work for other communities as well in
terms of here's what we have to offer.
If you need, to Katherine's point, if
you need a a sign interpreter for this,
if you need a translator, if you need
like visual, like what is it that these
particular communities need? Um,
and what does each one of them look
like? It may not be able to be
completely handtailored to each
community because that might be cost
prohibitive and you know it just but
what does what would it look like to
move in that direction? So that in
essentially it really is the full
definition of equity that everyone who
needs it and how they need it is able to
have access to it eventually in the
future. I don't know. Um, is anyone else
um has anything else to say or a
comment? Um, I would definitely see
there's someone's hand up. Zoe, did you
want to try again?
>> Yes. Is it working this time?
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Great. Um, I actually I I really,
you know, enjoyed listening you talk and
um, you really touched on a lot of great
points and I love how you talked about
bringing it to them, you know, in a way,
you know, where you kind of mentioned
maybe just giving them the option to,
you know, if you want it, it's here, you
know, cuz I do think, you know, in a lot
of, you know, um, more of the rural
communities and tribal areas, I'm I'm
familiar because, um, I do have family
that lives in New Mexico. I I didn't
write that in the thing because it would
have been too long. Um and um I have
some family that lives in like Hus
Pueblo and you know Albuquerque and then
they work in Santa Fe. So it's kind of
like there's a lot of gap um area and um
a lot of things can be very far. So if
somebody needs like a hospital or
anything like that, you know, and I
don't know how you guys do things of
course. So um you know I like that you
mentioned you know like okay here's the
option that we have but also um you know
maybe going to the communities. I know,
you know, you guys already in the
process of doing that and have your um
because from what I just heard um you
know, have your meetings and things like
that, but also I know in a lot of areas
like I can just tell you from like my
area in Buffalo, I work in um of course
and I work in an urban area. Um but um
there's a there's not a lot of access to
care in some of these areas. So we go to
them. Um, I don't do this anymore, but I
worked for a few years on an acute
community treatment team where we went
to people. And I was just thinking maybe
that's something that, you know,
eventually when this is all put together
of having people go there, you know,
maybe having, you know, I'm of course my
first thought, you know, being um a
nurse practitioner are nurses um and
social workers and people that can maybe
get trained and who are more familiar
with working with um you know, larger
populations and not afraid to go out
into the community. Um, those were just
some thoughts I was having because I was
thinking about the transportation issues
when you mentioned transportation. I
know it can be far, you know, like it
could be an hour away to go to get
somewhere and um, not everyone has that
access. So, um, yeah. So, I think you
brought up some amazing points. So, I
hope that I can continue coming to these
so I can maybe build on that too and
just think, you know, hopefully with
you. But, I just wanted to kind of
comment on that and I also wanted to
test out to see if I could even comment
anymore. But I I think I figured it out.
I got it. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> And Desba, we just have a couple of
minutes left and uh we do we are going
to have to close uh at time. Um but I
just wanted to to bring up uh we need to
do two things. We need to set the date
for the next meeting. And I would like
to recommend that at the next meeting,
we actually create a list of what are
those specific items that we need to
look at regarding equity and access and
and actually start uh naming them and
starting to look at potentially some
plans for how to address them. And so I
would recommend that for the next
meeting.
>> Yeah. Um
>> um I had it looked at let's see we got
three minutes now
>> and as far as calendar what I would
recommend is um we do have we we have
been asking the committees to hold off
until after the session. Um but a part
of that is uh then after the session we
have that next um two weeks has actually
gotten really busy with various other
meetings. So, I would recommend uh if
you wanted to stick with the evening
time, Wednesday, March 11th um at uh the
same time starting at 5:15.
>> Okay, I think that works. That works.
That works. That works.
And then just I will I I feel like there
I I I don't want to miss people who are
you know I will try to see if I can um
and I know that you guys will work with
me on this but I do want to make sure
that we do like a morning and an evening
at some point too as well. Um but that
but next meeting Wednesday March 11th
5:15 sounds good. I I mean, we'd be open
if you wanted to do that one as a a day
one and maybe do that one in the
afternoon starting at uh 1:00.
>> That sounds good. We'll do that.
>> So, so then Wednesday, March 11th at 100
p.m. starting at 1.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. We will get that scheduled then.
>> Okay. Sounds good. Yeah. And then we'll
definitely have more specifics um about
what to do. And thank you, you know, for
reminding me about the session. um you
know, we need to get these things out. I
just didn't want to kind of leave people
out and thinking, you know, that nothing
is is, you know, getting done about the
the uh equity fund or the tribes. It's
just it takes it takes some time to get
everyone else on board and on the same
page. But if any of you can please just
like you know in your own networks all
your friends you know um even if it is
to kind of light some fires under some
people um be like did you hear what they
said? Um can't believe they said that.
Um you need to come to the meeting. uh
just because it really we really do need
to hear um perspective and and and to me
like honestly I have learned so much
just by listening to people um but that
means that people need to speak up as
well and if there is some way we can
have that happen um where we can get
more people to speak up um this is
incredibly and vitally important to the
health of our community our mental
health from everyone your brothers and
your sisters everyone one is your
brother and your sister. I hope you all
have a good night. Thank you so much for
this. Thank you Dominic and Jorge and um
Ismiles. Appreciate your time.
Appreciate everyone's time. Have a great
night.
>> Thank you to everyone.
>> Thank you.